Robert Gatter

Saint Louis University School of Law Center for Health Law Studies 3700 Lindell Blvd., St. Louis MO 63108 rgatter@slu.edu (314) 977-3355

Current Position: Professor of Law, Co-Director of Center for Health Law Studies, Saint Louis University School of Law, July 2008 to present (with tenure), teaching *Health Care Law, Public Health Law, Theories of Health Law Seminar, Administrative Law, Contracts*

Prior Positions:

Penn State University, Dickinson School of Law, July 2000 through June 2008, Professor of Law (2006-2008 with tenure), Associate Dean for Academic Affairs (Jan. 2006 through June 2007), Associate Professor of Law (2004-2006), Assistant Professor of Law (2000-2004)

Visiting Assistant Professor of Law, Chicago-Kent College of Law, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago IL, 1997-2000

Fellow, Center for Bioethics, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis MN, 1996-1997

Adjunct Instructor, Center for the Study of Bioethics, Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee WI, 1995-1996

Associate Attorney, Davis Graham & Stubbs, Denver, CO, 1990-93

Education

University of Pennsylvania Law School, J.D., 1990

Medical College of Wisconsin, M.A. in Bioethics, 1995

Johns Hopkins University, B.A. in Social and Behavioral Sciences, 1986

Publications

Articles and Essays:

Shifting Public Health Priorities and the Global Effort to Prevent a Bird Flu (manuscript submitted to law journals) (2012).

Global Public Health Legal Responses to H1N1, 39 J. L. MED. & ETH. 46 (2011) (with Lance Gable, Brooke Courtney, and Eleanor Kinney)

Blowing Blotner: A Missed Opportunity to Mend Georgia's Informed Consent Law, 11 HOUS. J. HEALTH L. & POL'Y 79 (2011)

Symposium Foreword, Pandemic Preparedness: Lessons Learned and Future Challenges, 4 St. Louis U. J. Health L. & Pol'y 1 (2010)

A Prisoner's Constitutional Right to Medical Information: Doctrinally Flawed and a Threat to State Informed Consent Law, 45 WAKE FOREST L. REV. 1025 (2010)

Conflicts of Interest in International Human Drug Research and the Insufficiency of International Protections, 32 Am. J. L. & Med. 351 (2006)

The Mysterious Survival of the Policy Against Informed Consent Liability for Hospitals, 81 Notre Dame L. Rev. 1203 (2006)

Institutionally Sponsored Mediation and the Emerging Medical Trust Movement in the U.S., 23 Medicine & Law 201 (2004)

Faith, Confidence, and Health Care: Fostering Trust in Medicine through Law, 39 WAKE FOREST L. REV. 395 (2004)

Walking the Talk of Trust in Human Subjects Research: The Challenge of Regulating Financial Conflicts of Interest, 52 Emory L. J. 327 (2003)

Informed Consent Law and the Forgotten Duty of Physician Inquiry, 31 Loy. U. Chi. L.J. 557 (2000)

Unnecessary Adversaries at the End of Life: Preventing Erosion of the Patient-Physician Relationship by Mediating End-of-Life Treatment Disputes, 79 B.U. L. REV. 1091 (1999)

From Futility to Triage, 20 J. MED. & PHIL. 191 (1995) (with John Moskop)

Book Chapters:

The New Global Framework for Pandemic Influenza Virus and Vaccine Sharing, GLOBALIZATION OF HEALTH CARE: LEGAL AND ETHICAL CHALLENGES __ (Glenn Cohen ed., Oxford University Press, forthcoming 2012).

Financial Conflicts of Interest in Human Subjects Research: Domestic and International Issues in Legal Perspectives in Bioethics 29 (Ana S. Iltis, Sandra H. Johnson & Barbara A. Hinze eds, Routledge Annals in Bioethics series, 2008)

End-of-Life Medical Decisions and Other Ethical Issues in HEALTH CARE LAW DESK REFERENCE (Alison Barnes ed., ALI-ABA, 2001)

Book Reviews, Op-Eds, and Other Works:

The Uninsured and the Commerce Clause, St. Louis Post-Dispatch, Aug. 23, 2011 (Op-Ed)

World Too Complacent on Bird Flu, Atlanta Journal Constitution, Aug. 17, 2011 (Op-Ed)

Health Care Regulation in America: Complexity, Confrontation and Compromise by Robert I. Field, 28 J. LEG. MED. 593 (2007) (book review)

Yelling 'Yuck' at Cloning is not Rational, HARRISBURG PATRIOT-NEWS, Jan. 2, 2003, A9 (Op-Ed)

Should You Accept Gifts or Bequests from Patients?, Am. MED. NEWS, November 6, 2000

Qualifying to Wait: Some Ethics of Transplant Wait-listing, 8(3) CAMBRIDGE Q. HEALTHCARE ETH. 375 (Spring 1999) (response to case study)

Cloning Position Paper of IIT Institute of Science Law and Technology's Working Group on Reproductive Technologies, 8 So. CAL. INTERDISC. L. J. 87 (1998) (member of the working group that authored this position paper and primary author of the dissenting opinion)

ART into Science: Regulation of Fertility Techniques, 281 SCIENCE 651 (1998) (member of the working group that authored this policy statement)

Selected Panels and Presentations

Update on International Bird Flu Policy, presentation, ASLME Health Law Professors Conference, Arizona State University Law School, upcoming June 2012.

Roundtable Discussion on Censoring Bird Flu Studies, presentation, ASLME Health Law Professors Conference, Arizona State University Law School, upcoming June 2012.

Shifting Public Health Priorities and the Global Effort to Prevent a Bird Flu, invited Guest Scholar presentation, Southern Illinois University School of Law, upcoming April 2012

A Review of the Constitutional Challenges to Health Care Reform, St. Louis Area Health Lawyers Association, St. Louis MO, January 13, 2012

Defending the Constitutionality of Medicaid Expansion under Health Care Reform, Federalist Society Debate with Prof. James Blumstein of Vanderbilt University, November 10, 2011

Global Politics of Pandemic Influenza Vaccine-Sharing, presentation, Globalization of Health Care: Legal and Ethical Challenges, Petrie-Flom Center for Health Policy, Biotechnology and Bioethics, Harvard Law School, May 2011

WHO Pandemic Influenza Preparedness Framework and the Stalemate Over Virus and Vaccine Sharing, presentation, Using Law, Policy and Research to Improve the Public's Health: A National Conference, American Society of Law Medicine and Ethics and the Public Health Law Association, September 2010

Hospital Liability for Breaches of Informed Consent, St. Louis Area Health Lawyers Association, St. Louis MO, September 2010

International Attention on the Prevention of Animal Influenza: the Hanoi Declaration, presentation, Health Law Teachers Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Law Medicine and Ethics and University of Texas School of Law, June 2010

On Overview of Health Law and Health Care Reform (with Prof. Tim Greaney), invited presentation, Annual Meeting of the Council of University Chairs of Obstetrics and Gynecology, San Francisco CA, April 2010

Pandemic Preparedness: Lessons Learned and Future Challenges, Organizer and Moderator, 22nd Annual Health Law Symposium, Center for Health Law Studies, Saint Louis University School of Law, St. Louis MO, March 2010

Substantive Due Process and Disclosure Duties under State Informed Consent Laws, presentation, Health Law Teachers Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Law Medicine and Ethics and Case Western Reserve University School of Law, June 2009

New Governance Theory and Health Law, organizer and moderator, Law, Medicine and Health Care section panel, AALS Annual Meeting, Washington DC, Jan. 2007

Conflicts of Interest in International Human Drug Research and the Insufficiency of International Protections, presentation, Symposium on Regulatory Issues of the Globalization of Pharmaceuticals, Boston University School of Law, Boston MA, Feb. 2006

Regulatory Implications of the Flu Vaccine Shortage, presentation, Health Law Teachers Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Law Medicine and Ethics and University of Houston Law Center, Houston TX, June 2005

Current Issues in Drug Regulation, moderator of academic panel, Health Law Teachers Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Law Medicine and Ethics and University of Houston Law Center, Houston TX, June 2005

Law and Medicine in Three Dimensions: Reconstructing a Health Care Regulatory Continuum, poster presentation, Health Law Teachers Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Law, Medicine and Ethics and Seton Hall University School of Law, Newark NJ, June 2004

The Racial Blind Spot of an Emerging Medical Trust Movement, Mid-Atlantic People of Color Conference, Washington & Lee University School of Law, Lexington VA, Jan. 2003

Trust-Oriented Health Law: Implications and Challenges, work-in-progress presentation at the Health Law Scholars Workshop sponsored by the American Society of Law, Medicine and Ethics, St. Louis MO, Oct. 2002

Regulating Financial Conflicts of Interest, presentation at the Human Subjects Research session of the Health Law Teachers Conference sponsored by the American Society of Law, Medicine and Ethics, Indianapolis IN, June 2002

The Budget Barrier and Other Legal Impediments to Community-Based Treatment, presentation during a session on access to community-based care for the disabled, Annual Meeting of the American Society for Bioethics and Humanities, Nashville, Tennessee, Oct. 2001

Service Activities and Memberships:

Member, Editorial Board, AJOB – PRIMARY RESEARCH (2010-present)

Symposium Organizer, 22nd Annual Health Law Symposium, Center for Health Law Studies, Saint Louis University School of Law, held March 2010.

Executive Committee member, Law, Medicine and Health Care Section, Association of American Law Schools, 2007-2009 academic year (Chair 2007-2008, Chair-Elect 2006-2007 academic year, Secretary 2005-2006), and member of section since 2000

Nominating Committee, Health Law Scholars Workshop, American Society of Law, Medicine and Ethics, 2003-present

Reader and Panelist, Health Law Scholars Workshop, American Society of Law, Medicine and Ethics, hosted by Saint Louis University School of Law, Sept 2009 and 2010

Member, Academia Advisory Group, American Health Lawyers Assoc., 2005-2009

Member, Advisory Panel, Conflicts of Interest Notification Study (COINS), a research project funded by the National Institutes of Health (Jeremy Sugarman, principal investigator), 2004-2007

Member, Board of Visitors, Southern Illinois University School of Law, 2004-2006

Member, Ethics Committee, Keystone Human Services, Harrisburg PA, 2000-2003

Member, American Health Lawyers Association

Member or Chair of various institutional committees at St. Louis University School of Law, including faculty advisor to the Saint Louis University Journal of Health Law and Policy (2008-present), Admissions Committee (Chair 2010-present), and Ad Hoc Committee on Law School Progress in US News Ranking (summer 2010); and at Penn State - Dickinson School of Law, including Academic Rules (member Spring 2005, 2005-2006, 2006-2007 and Chair Spring and Summer 2007), Admissions (member 2002-2003 and Chair 2003-2004, 2004-2005, and 2007-2008), Appointments (member 2005-2006, 2006-2007), Building Program (member Spring 2005, 2005-2006), Curriculum (member 2005-2006, 2006-2007 and Chair Fall 2005), Dean Search (member 2001-2002), Faculty Development (member 2002-2003), Self-Study (member 2007-2008) and Technology (member 2000-2001); also Secretary of the Penn State – Dickinson School of Law Faculty (2007-2008)

Member, Penn State University Bioethics Advisory Committee (2007-2008)